National Captive Nations Committee Collection
National Captive Nations Committee Collection
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Prospectus, circa 1964; 1 prospectus (Box 5)
  - Public Law 86-90, 1959 (Box 5)
    Different copies of the Resolution written by Dobriansky which was signed into law by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in 1959.
  - Publications, 1960-1973 (Box 5)
    Publications by the NCNC and its chapters. Includes pamphlets, bulletins, fliers, cards, commemorative stamps and brochure.
  - Publications of miscellaneous organizations, 1966-1977 (Box 5)
    Pamphlets and other printed material. Organizations include: American Conservative Union, Manion Forum Newsletter, Czechoslovak National Council of America, S.O. Jarpa of the National Party of Chile, the Mexican Government, Morris Rothenberg of the Center for Advanced International Studies at the University of Miami, Victor Lasky and the American-Chilian Council, James D. Theberge and the American Chilean Council, James P. Lucier and the Committee on Latin America, National Strategy Information Center, Inc., Students in Defense of Human Rights in the Soviet Union, Ukrainian Student Organization of Michnowsky, Takeshi Furuta and the International Federation for Victory over Communism (Japan), British League for European Freedom, Yaroslav Stetsko and the Press Bureau of the Antibolshevik Bloc of Nations, Committee for the Defense of Valentyn Moroz, The Christophers, the Ukrainian Bicentennial Committee of America and the United Committee of Ukrainian Organizations of New York.
  - Resolutions 211 (1961), 14(1965) and 106 (1973): Special Committee on the Captive Nations, 1960-1973 (Box 5)
    See Also Flood, Daniel J..
    Dobriansky and others made repeated efforts to create a special committee to address the captive nations. Resolutions 211, 14 and 106 were submitted by Danield Flood. Folder includes signed petitions mailed in to the NCNC, letters of support from the North Shore Chapter “General Stefanik” of the Czechoslovak National Council of America and American Friends of Anti-Bolshevik Bloc of Nations, Inc., and congressional records of remarks from Danield L. Flood, Edward J. Derwinski, and Thaddeus J. Dulski.
  - Schlafly, Phyllis, 1971-1978 (Box 6)
    Wife of Fred Schlafly, president of the ACWF. Includes issues of the Phyllis Schlafly Report, personal correspondence and a newspaper clipping of "Captive Nations Week."
  - Ukrainian Congress Committee of America
    - Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 6)
      See Also Dobriansky, Lev E..
      Dr. Dobriansky was president of the UCCA. Includes annual mass-distibuted letters to politicians asking for observation and support of Ukraine’s Independence Day, January 22, 1918. Includes a translation reprint of a 1974 Boris Bannov article and response from Dobriansky as well as other news releases.
    - Resolutions 48, 49, 165, 92, and 18: Resurrecting the Ukrainian Churches, 1970-1981 (Box 6)
      Multiple resolutions were submitted by Representatives Flood, Derwinski, Annunzio, Burke, Delaney, Dodd, Giaimo, Koch, Moakley, Patten, Sarasin, Stratton, Walsh and Wydler to seek the resurrection of the Ukrainian Orthodox and Catholic Churches in Ukraine. Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, and congressional records.
    - Resolutions 979,1126, 1127, and 455: Ukrainian Independence Day, 1965-1978 (Box 6)
      Multiple resolutions were submitted by Representatives Flood, Derwinski, Stratton, Minshall, Dulski, Schaderberg, Bush, Zukowsky, Kleppe, and Schweiker. The resolutions call for a Presidential Proclamation of Ukrainian Independence Day every January 22nd. Includes correspondence with politicians, resolutions, and congressional records.
    - Ukrainian Bulletin, 1960-1966; 7 issues (Box 6)
      See Also Dobriansky, Lev E.: Publications and Statements.
      Published semi-monthly by the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.
  - The White House, 1969-1979 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence with White House that is not exclusively related to Captive Nations Week. Presidents span from Nixon to Carter.
  - World Anti-Communist League (WACL)
    See Also Ku, Cheng-kang.
    - 1967 Conference (Box 6)
      Includes the WACL charter, conference program, handbook of information, correspondence about preparations, and a statement by Dr. Dobriansky introducing the NCNC.
    - 1968 Conference, Sep 1968 - Feb 1969 (Box 6)
      The conference was held between December 15-20 in Saigon. Folder includes Congressional Record of remarks by Derwinski as well as correspondence between Dr. Ku and Dr. Dobriansky.
    - 1969 Conference, Jan - Feb 1970 (Box 6)
      The conference was held in Bangkok, Thailand in December of 1969. Folder contains correspondence and a clipping of an address given by Dobriansky at the conference from the WACL Bulletin.
    - 1970 Conference, Jan - Oct 1970 (Box 6)
      This was a combined conference: the 4th WACL and the 16th APACL conferences, held in Tokyo in September of 1970. Folder includes correspondence and conference information.
    - 1971 Conference, Jul - Sep 1971 (Box 6)
      Combined 5th WACL and 17th APACL conference held in Quezon City, Philippines. Folder includes invitation to a reception for the delegates, conference program, and correspondence.
    - 1972 Conference, Aug - Nov 1972 (Box 6)
      The 6th WACL conference was held in tandem with the 4th World Youth Anti-Communist League (WYACL) conference in Mexico City from August 25-27, 1972. Dobriansky did not attend. Folder includes correspondence, the NCNC resolution submitted for the WACL conference and a table sign.
    - 1973 Conference, Dec 1972 - Aug 1973 (Box 6)
      This conference was planned as the 7th WACL conference in London between August 29th and September 1st of 1973, but because the British government would not grant Dr. Ku a temporary visa, the conference was abandoned by the ACWF and Dobriansky. The folder includes planning material and correspondence.
    - 1974 Conference, Nov 1973 - May 1974 (Box 6)
      The 1973 conference having been problematic, this 1974 conference became the 7th WACL conference and was held in Washington, D.C. between April 8th and 11th, 1974. Folder includes large quantity of statements and reports as presented at the conference.
    - 1975 Conference, Jul 1975 (Box 6)
      Contains letter from Lee Edwards of ACWF and address by Fred Schlafly, president of ACWF, as given at the 8th WACL conference held in Rio de Janeiro in April, 1975.
    - 1976 Conference, Dec 1975 (Box 6)
      Contains two documents from WACL Executive Board meetings in preparation for the 9th conference held in 1976.
    - 1979 Conference, Apr 1979 (Box 6)
      Contains a clipping from Asian Outlook with a color picture of the inaugural session at the 12th WACL conference held in Asuncion, Paraguay.
    - 1981 Conference, Apr - Jun 1981 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence and a draft program for the 14th WACL conference held in Taipei, Taiwan between July 31st and August 4th, 1981.
    - World Freedom Day 1970, Oct 1969 - Jan 1970 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence planning World Freedom Day, January 23rd, 1970. Maine Senator Margaret Chase Smith was scheduled to attend the events but canceled January 19th because of Senate voting.
    - World Freedom Day 1971, Nov 1970 - Feb 1971 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence.
    - World Freedom Day 1972, Dec 1971 - Feb 1972 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence. Senator Buckley attended the events in Taipei.
    - World Freedom Day 1973, Oct 1972 - Feb 1973 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence. Congressman W.C. Daniel attended the events in Taipei.
    - World Freedom Day 1974, Nov 1973 - Feb 1974 (Box 6)
      Contains photographs and a Mass Rally Program for January 23rd, 1974 as well as correspondence. Senator Jesse A. Helms attended the events in Taipei.
    - World Freedom Day 1975, Oct 1974 - Feb 1975 (Box 6)
      Correspondence about the events which featured Congressmen John T. Myers and other international dignitaries and politicians.
    - World Freedom Day 1976, Nov 1975 - Jan 1976 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence and "Guidelines for 1976 World Freedom Day Campaign."
    - World Freedom Day 1977, Jan 1977 (Box 6)
      1 letter from Dr. Ku to Dr. Dobriansky.
    - World Freedom Day 1978, Jan 1978 (Box 6)
    - World Freedom Day 1979, Jan 1979 (Box 6)
      1 letter from Dr. Dobriansky to Dr. Ku. Representative Rudd visited Taipei for World Freedom Day in 1979.
    - World Freedom Day 1980, Nov 1979 - Feb 1980 (Box 6)
      Correspondence.
    - World Freedom Day 1981, Nov 1980 - Mar 1981 (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence. Congressman John Wydler attended the events in Taipei.
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      Contains a 1972 press release called "WACL Honorary Chairman Dr. Ku Cheng-kang's Statement on President Richard M. Nixon's Chinese Mainland Visit," circulars from WACL, and a "Report from Sweden" from the WACL chapter there called the Democratic Alliance.
  - World Youth Anti-Communist League, 1973 (Box 6)
    Also called the Liga Mundial Juvenil Anticomunista and the Ligue Mondiale de la Jeunesse Anticommuniste. Includes 2 circulars and 1 announcement from 1973.
  - Miscellaneous, 1960-1981 (Box 6)
    Includes undated biographical sketches for Frank T.T. Sia, Petras P. Dauzvardis, Joseph C. Murphy, and Dobriansky. Includes two submissions for organization directories.